I think it must be a year or two ago, I
covered a number of randomized control
trials that indicated strongly that the
nutrient zeazanthin is able to slow the
loss of vision by macular degeneration.
For that reason alone, it crossed from
this has potential to this has true
realworld impact. However, recently a
fascinating study released that
implicates zeazanthin as not only a
great eye supplement but an
anti-cancerous molecule as well. Now, if
you know my style, I was curious if
we've been sleeping on other studies
that point the same direction. And guess
what? We have. So, how strong is the
evidence for zeazanthin and its cancer
protection effects? Is the evidence on
par with the eye health effects? and
what is the one food that can help us
avoid supplementation because it is a
potent zeazanthin carrier. Stay tuned.
Like I mentioned, when we look at the
broader literature, there's a generally
consistent trend that people that either
consume more or have higher blood values
of zeazanthin have reduced risk of a few
different assessed cancers spec
specifically breast cancer and bladder
cancer. However, there are also studies
that indicate no effect. But I hold
these studies with lower weight on the
conclusions because they tend to be much
smaller and less methodologically sound.
When we focus on bigger, better studies
in women looking at the consumption of
zeazanthin over 14 years, those women
consuming the most had a notable
reduction in the risk of breast cancer
overall. Now, I'm pointing out this
study because the design of that the
researchers used was able to control for
family history, age, energy intake,
menopause, hormone use, and more factors
that directly affect breast cancer risk.
All that said, however, other studies,
even those that agree, tend to have much
weaker method methodology and
insufficient controls for influencing
factors like the ones that I mentioned.
Either way, there is a consistent trend
in the higher quality evidence that if
consumed zeazanthin is greater, there is
a reduced risk of cancer. Still,
everything combined, the wider scope of
the data all points in the direction of
zeazanthin benefit against cancer with
the most robust evidence being against
breast cancer, weak evidence against
bladder cancer, and more data needed on
all other forms of cancer. Still, just
because there's no data doesn't mean
that there's no effect. So what does
this recent study tell us? Essentially
zeizanthin was identified as a molecule
of interest because it is increased in
the killing of cancer cells. After this
identification, the zeizanthin was fed
to different groups of mice with two
different forms of cancer seen here. You
can see the schematic of the
experimental design. Mice were given
cancer at which point they probably wish
that they'd made better friends because
their giftgiving was less than
desirable. But putting that aside, the
mice were then fed zeizanthin up top or
not the control condition on the bottom.
Then on the right side, these two graphs
are measures of tumor size over time.
The lower the lines are, the better
because it's a smaller tumor, less
cancer progression by this measure. Now,
I don't need to spell it out for you.
The zeizanthin condition, regardless of
the cancer type, reduce cancer growth.
But this introduces a new aspect to the
story because the researchers identified
that the mechanism by which zeizanthin
pulls off these effects is through the
activation of TE-C cells, the
specialized type of immune cells that
attack cancer cells. These tea cells
once more active are more likely to
multiply to send out specialized
inflammatory molecules to recruit more
immune cells as well as release directly
damaging molecules called perforin and
granzymes that damage the cancer cell.
But just because zeazanthin seems to be
effective doesn't mean that uh it can't
use some help. In fact, when we look at
tumor growth again, the higher the
lines, the worse. And we see zeazanthin
causes the predictable reduction in
tumor size. But it is much more
effective when it's paired with
imunotherapy where the tumor is really
blasted down.
This then means in preliminary research
that zeazanthin allows specialized
immune cells, T-C cells, to be more
active and aggressive against cancer
cells. And this effect is especially
potent when paired with imunotherapies.
Now, this is all pretty compelling
evidence, but we need to come back out
of our cells and look at the big picture
again because there's a critical piece
of context that needs to be applied
here. And on top of that, there's a
particular food that could offer us all
these benefits that we've been going
over at a very small amount of
consumption. Now, I'll get into all that
next, but let's assume that you wanted
more information on zeazanthin and
breast cancer or wanted to understand
exactly how zeazanthin activates our
immune cells or what are independent
reputable brands to get zeazanthin from
at a proper dose. Then consider checking
out the full analysis, the extension of
this video that you're watching. It's
included with my Physionic Insider
membership along with an article to
accompany every single video that's
released over the last few years, plus a
monthly private podcast, a master
supplement list on what works and what
doesn't, and man, just so much more. If
you're interested, check out the
Physionic Insiders using the link in the
description. First, let's discuss this
critical context. There's two things.
One, you'll often hear about zeazanthin
paired with its sibling molecule
luteine, especially in the eye health
literature, and admittedly many of the
studies look at these molecules in
combination. However, the main study
that we went over focused on zeazanthin,
though they did look at luteine as well.
I'll discuss more on that in my extended
analysis. But here's what you should
know. We're focusing on zeazanthin
because this study focused on it. And
although most of the evidence in humans
looks at both molecules together, making
it difficult to really separate the
effects according to zeazanthin or
luteine driving the effect, there are
some studies that indicate a cancer
protective effect of zeazanthin in
isolation. That does not mean that
luteine is not effective and I plan on
actually covering that in more depth in
future content as luteine tells a
slightly different story and would
detract from this one. So to be clear,
our focus is on zeazanthin, but luteine
may also be effective and we'll assess
that at a separate time. So stay tuned
for that. The second point is that
unlike the eye health data which was
heavily focused on direct intervention
studies, i.e. randomized control trials,
we're combining animal focused
mechanistic data with long-term human
data, so associative data. So when I
asked at the beginning if the evidence
is on par with the eye health effects,
the answer up to now is no. That doesn't
mean that the evidence is weak,
especially if we expand our view to
carotenoids in general, the class of
molecules that zeazanthin belongs to.
These data still indicate with moderate
certainty that zeazanthin is a cancer
fighting molecule. In the end,
considering the growing evidence across
multiple fronts, it seems a no-brainer
to focus some attention to consuming
zeazanthin. That brings us to my promise
of avoiding supplementation by focusing
on a particular food that contains
incredibly impressive levels of
zeazanthin within it. It's the wolf
berry. The side effect is that you feel
drawn to the city of London where you
turn into a werewolf and terrorize the
Londoners.
I won't confirm or deny that, but
another name for the wolf berry is the
goji berry. And it is filled with an
intense amount of zeazanthin. In fact,
based on rough estimates from all these
studies, as little as 10 grams of dried
goji berry would be sufficient to put
you in the higher consuming groups of
these studies with reduced risk of
cancer. This is especially nice because
goji berries can have side effects like
interactions with particular drugs. So,
as is always the case, you should
consult with your physician if you're on
blood pressure or blood thinning or
other like drugs. That's a low calorie,
less than one serving size, potent way
of getting zeazanthin. Winwin. Anyway,
if you want more concrete benefits of
zeazanthin, check this sucker out. And
if you decide to eat wolf berries, uh
maybe have a friend lock you up on the
full moon. And if you wake up dazed and
confused in a zoo, maybe cut back a bit.
Just a friendly bit of advice.